{"tossups": [{"question": "John Shipton chaired a political party founded by this man to contest the 2013 Australian Senate elections. An organization founded by this man gained prominence after publishing the \u201cCollateral Murder\u201d video, along with other materials provided by Chelsea Manning. In 2010, Sweden requested that this man be extradited on allegations of sexual assault. This man was granted asylum by Ecuador in 2012, and currently resides in its London embassy. For ten points, name this whistleblower who founded WikiLeaks.", "answer": "Julian (Paul)<b> Assange</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "At the age of four, this figure visited Pope Leo IV, who supposedly \u201canointed\u201d this man as king. From a later pope, Marinus, this man may have received a fragment of the true cross, according to this man\u2019s bishop Asser. He and a rival split the kingdom of Mercia, the eastern half of which joined the kingdom of East Anglia, and this king later rid Wessex of the Danes. For ten points, name this only English monarch to be stylized \u201cthe Great.\u201d", "answer": "<b> Alfred</b> the Great (or<b> Alfred</b> I)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Physicists often use the \u201cLeft step\u201d alternative to this system; another famous alternative was created by Theodor Benfey in a spiral shape. The most recent change to this system included an addition named for the state of Tennessee. This system initially had blank spaces left for \u201ceka-germanium\u201d and other undiscovered entries. Dmitri Mendeleev introduced, for ten points, what system that organizes the 118 chemical elements?", "answer": "<b> periodic table</b> of the elements", "metadata": "Science - Chemistry"}, {"question": "This man led a campaign to boycott school textbooks produced by<em> Harper\u2019s</em> to blackmail the company into firing one of its employees. The Committee of Seventy investigated the actions of this man. During this man\u2019s trial, he fled home arrest and escaped to Spain, but he was recognized from his depiction in a political cartoon drawn by Thomas Nast. For ten points, identify this corrupt leader of Tammany Hall.", "answer": "William M. \u201cBoss\u201d<b> Tweed</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The loser of this event began it wearing a \u201cSugar Daddy\u201d jacket, having been sponsored by the candy. This event, which took place four months after a similar event lost by Margaret Court, was watched by 50 million people and ended in straight sets. A 2017 film starring Emma Stone and Steve Carell depicts, for ten points, what 1973 match in which Billie Jean King defeated Bobby Riggs, helping spark interest in women\u2019s tennis?", "answer": "<b>Battle</b> <b>of</b> <b>the</b> <b>Sexes</b> (accept descriptive answers related to Billie Jean <b>King</b> <b>playing/defeating/etc.</b> Bobby<b> Riggs</b> before \u201cBillie\u201d is read)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "A leader of this kingdom founded the League of Corinth after crushing the Sacred Band of Thebes at Chaeronea [care-oh-nay-uh]. After a leader of this empire died, its generals feuded in the Wars of the Diadochi [die-ah-doe-kee], which produced the Ptolemaic Kingdom and Seleucid Empire. A leader of this kingdom defeated Darius III at the Battle of Issus before conquering Babylon at the Battle of Gaugamela. For ten points, name this kingdom led by Philip II and Alexander the Great.", "answer": "Kingdom of<b> Macedon</b>ia", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "This event\u2019s lesser known victims include the Batwa pygmy people. The French attempted to alleviate this event through a safe zone in Operation Turquoise. The destruction of an aircraft carrying Juvenal Habyarimana was used as a pretext to begin this event, which ended when Paul Kagame\u2019s [kah-gah-may\u2019s] Patriotic Front defeated the Interahamwe and recaptured Kigali. For ten points, name this 1994 atrocity in which the Hutus targeted Tutsis in an East African country.", "answer": "<b> Rwanda</b>n<b> Genocide</b> (accept descriptions of the<b> genocide of the Tutsis</b>/<b>by the Hutus </b>until \u201cHutu\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Highwayman William Brazelton operated around this city in the mid-19th century. Hugh O\u2019Connor founded this non-Mexican city as a military fort in 1775. McKale Center in this city is home to its state\u2019s flagship university. Saguaro National Park is located just west of this city, where Jared Lee Loughner attempted to assassinate Representative Gabrielle Giffords in 2011. For ten points, name this home of the University of Arizona, the second largest city in Arizona.", "answer": "<b> Tucson</b>, Arizona", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This ruler failed to negotiate a trade agreement with Japan after storms blew a Japanese sea captain into this ruler\u2019s territory. This ruler established the first publicly funded higher-education institution for women, the Smolny Institute. She eliminated required military service for the nobility and placed Stanislas Poniatowski, her former lover, on the throne of Poland in 1763. This ruler assumed power after a coup d\u2019etat against her husband, Peter III. For ten points, name this \u201cGreat\u201d Empress of Russia.", "answer": "<b> Catherine</b> the Great (or<b> Catherine</b> II)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "For ten points, name this British philosopher, the co-author of<em> Principia Mathematica</em>.", "answer": "Bertrand<b> Russell</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "Treaties concerning this subject included SALT I, SALT II, and START.", "answer": "<b> nuclear weapons</b> (accept answers about<b> nuclear proliferation</b>,<b> nuclear</b> weapon<b> test</b>ing, <b>nuclear war</b>fare, etc.; accept specific types of nuclear weapons; prompt on answers related to (ballistic) missiles)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Philip Murray represented workers in this industry, who went on strike in April 1952 in response to Harry Truman\u2019s nationalization of its production facilities, a decision that was quickly ruled unconstitutional in the<em> Youngstown</em> case. ArcelorMittal, the world\u2019s largest producer of this commodity, absorbed a major American company in this industry, Bethlehem, during the 2000s. For ten points, name this industrial commodity that created much of Andrew Carnegie\u2019s wealth in Pittsburgh.", "answer": "<b> steel</b> industry", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "In a novel in this genre, the prostitute Lorena suffers from PTSD after she is kidnapped and sexually assaulted by Blue Duck. A novel in this genre follows Jane Withersteen, who escapes from a Mormon commune. Books in this genre include Larry McMurtry\u2019s<em> Lonesome Dove</em> and Zane Grey\u2019s<em> Riders of the</em> <em>Purple Sage</em>. For ten points, what is the genre of many Louis L\u2019Amour novels featuring cowboys?", "answer": "<b> Western</b>s (accept<b> Western</b> fiction; accept<b> Frontier</b> fiction)", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Long Fiction"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "In 1950, this politician distributed a \u201cPink Sheet\u201d attacking the voting record of his opponent, Helen Gahagan Douglas. After this man lost a 1962 election to Pat Brown, this man claimed to give his last press conference and told the media they \u201cwon\u2019t have [him] to kick around anymore.\u201d This man refused to wear makeup in the first televised presidential debate, which pitted him against John F. Kennedy. Dwight Eisenhower\u2019s Vice President was, for ten points, what politician who resigned as President after the Watergate scandal?", "answer": "Richard Milhous<b> Nixon</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>During the construction of the Overland Telegraph Line, this site was first explored by Ernest Giles and William Gosse. This site was secured by Bob Hawke in a 99-year lease</b> <b>that controversially allowed it to be (+)</b> <b>climbed by visitors. This site forms a national</b> <b>park along with the Kata Tjuta, a series of formations also called the Olgas. This site was originally named in honor of Henry (*)</b> Ayers. For ten points, name this sandstone formation that is sacred to the Anangu Aboriginal people of Australia\u2019s Northern Territory.", "answer": "<b> Uluru</b> (accept<b> Ayers Rock</b> before \u201cAyers\u201d is read)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b>An emperor of this dynasty was captured by the Oirat Esen Tayisi in the Tumu Crisis. Li Zicheng of the Shun Dynasty helped cause the downfall of this empire, which was founded</b> <b>by the (+)</b> <b>Hongwu Emperor. This dynasty, which was founded after the Red Turban</b> <b>revolt, was led by the Yongle Emperor, who built the (*)</b> Forbidden City and sponsored several treasure voyages under the eunuch Zheng He. For ten points, name this Chinese dynasty that followed the Qing and was known its for blue and white ceramic vases.", "answer": "<b> Ming</b> Dynasty", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>This man selected John Kern as his running mate in one election, in which his slogan was \u201cShall the People Rule?\u201d This man, a regular on the Chatauqua circuit, resigned as (+) Secretary of State in protest of Woodrow Wilson\u2019s pro-war stance. He rose to prominence after delivering an oration at an 1896 convention supporting (*) </b> bimetallism, demanding that Republicans not \u201ccrucify mankind\u201d on the title object. For ten points, name this Democratic presidential candidate who delivered the \u201cCross of Gold\u201d speech.", "answer": "William Jennings<b> Bryan</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>During this battle, the brother of Aeschylus [ess-kuh-luss] was cut down while attempting to pull a ship to shore by hand. Datis and Artaphernes were aided in this battle by a vengeful (+) Hippias, who had been exiled earlier by the winning side. Callimachus cast the deciding vote in favor of launching this battle, which resulted in a rout of (*)</b> Darius\u2019 men. Athens was victorious over Persia in, for ten points, what 490 BC battle that inspires the name of a lengthy footrace?", "answer": "Battle of<b> Marathon</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}